all right
[Music]
hibiscus tea also known as Roselle or
Jamaica is enjoyed around the world hot
or cold for its bright red color and
tart cranberry like Flavor it's The Zing
in red Zinger tea I talk about its
benefits in the chapter on high blood
pressure and how not to die working as
well as some leading anti-hypertensive
medications and head-to-head tests
or even beating the drugs out
within three hours of drinking hibiscus
tea changes in hundreds of metabolites
can be detected in the human bloodstream
with creative names like hibiscus acid
or hibiscus or hibis citrine alterations
in human gene expression of the
three-hour Mark after drinking it
suggests a down regulation of
cholesterol synthesis and an improvement
in metabolism but randomized control
trials failed to consistently find
cholesterol lowering benefits an
interesting side effect popped up though
weight loss
in Mexico hibiscus tea has been
traditionally used as a treatment for
obesity sparking lots of research
interest computer modeling Studies have
suggested that certain hibiscus
compounds might bind to the fat
digesting enzyme-like paste like a
locking key test tube studies screening
a variety of medicinal plants did indeed
find hibiscus inhibited lipase more than
most of the others and hibiscus has been
found to reduce body fat in hamsters
mice
and rats
increasing fecal fat excretion but it
wasn't tested in people until this study
published in 2014. the title gives the
findings away spoiler alert hibiscus can
inhibit obesity and fat accumulation in
humans and improve fatty liver
to create a randomized double-blind
trial instead of trying to create some
artificially colored and flavored
Placebo tea they just dried the hibiscus
tea into powder and put it into capsules
after 12 weeks there was a greater
reduction in waistlines and percent body
fat in the Hibiscus group compared to
those who got Placebo capsules but the
dose they ended up using was equivalent
of like nine cups of hibiscus tea a day
I recommend people stick to no more than
a quarter day on a regular basis due to
the high manganese content manganese is
an essential Trace mineral but nine cups
a day might result in too much of a good
thing
finally in 2018 this study was published
using a reasonable dose the equivalent
of about a single 12 ounce glass of
hibiscus tea a day the complicating
factor is that they also added Lemon
Verbena to the mix that's another herbal
tea better known for improving recovery
after intense bouts of strength training
but there was some promising in vitro
data on effects of lemon verbena on fat
cells in a Petri dish so they tried a
combination it comes out to be about a
cup and a half of hibiscus tea and a
quarter cup of lemon verbena tea once a
day for two months both the tea and
Placebo groups were fed diets containing
the same amount of calories yet those
randomized to the tea group lost
significantly more weight five pounds
compared to three pounds that's only an
extra pound or two a month but an extra
pound a month eating the same number of
calories that's the advantage of fat
blocking interventions actually cause
you to lose more calories Beyond just
reducing hunger and making you feel
Fuller longer and hope you'll eat fewer
calories in the first place
why not just pop pills instead of
brewing tea there's all sorts of herbal
extract supplements on the market but
that presumes we know enough to extract
out the right active ingredients for
example it does not appear to be the red
and the sign in pigments in hibiscus
since white varieties seem to have
similar effects when the various
compounds in hibiscus tea are isolated
out and tested in various combinations
synergistic effects are found meaning
the whole may be greater than the sum of
its parts as with any sour food or
beverage though like after eating Citrus
it's important to wash the natural acids
off your teeth by rinsing your mouth out
with water to protect your tooth enamel
you also want to wait at least an hour
before brushing so as not to erode your
enamel when it's in a softened state
[Music]
thank you